Hi, welcome back to
the Nagarjuna series.
And we're now in class number three.
We're ready to attack the chapters.
We're ready to get into the six chapters
of the 27 chapters,
which we're going to cover
in this particular session
of Nagarjuna teaching, session four.
This first chapter we're
going to cover is Chapter 18.
And as I mentioned earlier,
we're going to do six chapters,
18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23.
And pay close attention to Chapter 18.
I'm going to give you the
names of these six chapters
just to wet your appetite.
And then we'll go into them.
By the way, I hope as I mention
these six chapter names,
that you are already
in the mood to guess...
what's the connection?
And if you're like me, you're
going to hear the six names,
and you're going to say
"I don't see exactly
how one would flow into the other."
But that's not my problem.
That's your problem.
Okay, here we go.
Chapter 18 is called,
"An Investigation of
the Person and Things."
And most of you know this classic division
of all emptiness, into the emptiness
of Michael and the emptiness of things.
Or sometimes you can
say the emptiness of me
and the emptiness of mine,
meaning all the things around me
and the other parts of me.
So you can say, now we're going
to investigate the emptiness
of the person, and then
sometimes you can say things
in the universe.
Sometimes they specifically
say the parts of Michael.
And some sophisticated
commentators will say,
the universe as one of
the parts of Michael,
because Michael perceives the universe.
So really the universe becomes
just another part of Michael.
And I wanted to point out
that this chapter we're going
to start with, Chapter 18,
it's a really, really popular chapter.
I would say, as I mentioned
before, Chapter 18
and Chapter 24,
which we're going to cover next session,
of Nagarjuna teachings.
18 is extremely popular.
You've heard me talk about it.
You've heard many teachers
talk about this emptiness of me
and the emptiness of my parts.
And it's an extremely
important emptiness. Why?
Because it's the first link,
misunderstanding me and
misunderstanding my parts,
is the first link of the Wheel of Life.
It's called...
What's the technical name?
The strange technical name of that?
'JIG TSOGS LA LTA BA
The view of the perishable assemblage.
And it's a special kind of
misunderstanding of the world
which triggers all our personal suffering.
So it's one that you should learn.
All right, so, I actually had
some Mixed Nuts help me out,
especially Word Smith and Nick Lashaw.
And I said check all
the chapters of the 27,
tell me which are the most quoted chapters
in the last 1,000 years
of commentary by the
great Tibetan writers.
And they said, "Yeah, this Chapter 18
"is a very, very popular chapter."
And the only one which is
close to it is Chapter 24.
24 is an examination of
the four higher truths,
the four Arya truths.
That's going to be actually
the single most popular chapter
of all of them.
So we'll get to that next term.
But in this term, we're
starting with Chapter 18,
which by itself is then probably
the most important chapter
of the whole work.
So get yourself ready.
Get your thinking cap on for Chapter 18.
Chapter 19, is "An Investigation of Time."
Past, present and future.
How does that flow from
the emptiness of me
and my universe
is an Einstein question.
So you guys are supposed
to think about that.
From the investigating
the emptiness of Michael
and Michael's world, Michael's universe,
we go directly to investigating
the nature of time itself.
And we included a lot of those
ideas from the 19th chapter,
in the DCI presentation of time management
because there are ways to modify time.
There are ways to stretch time.
If you want to get more things done,
I encourage you to take that course,
the time management course of DCI.
I think it's Level 11.
Okay, good.
Okay, Chapter 20 is a very sexy chapter.
My teacher would say, "Oh? The
other chapters aren't sexy?"
No, they are, but this one's really sexy.
It's called, "An Investigation
of How Causes and
Conditions Come Together,"
how they converge.
And there's an expression there
called, what's is it called?
The ultimate convergence.
Consummate convergence
of causes and conditions.
What's it mean for causes and conditions
to come together in a perfect way?
And what are the implications
of the perfect coming together
of causes and conditions?
Shouldn't that trigger
a result immediately?
Once you get all the necessary causes
and all the necessary conditions:
you have a flower seed,
then you have fertilizer,
warmth, water, time, gardener,
then shouldn't that consummate collection
of causes and conditions
immediately trigger a result?
And where's the emptiness there?
That's Chapter 20.
Chapter 21. Once you talk about
and all we've talked about so
far in the first 20 chapters
would be how things happen.
Then wouldn't it be natural to talk about
how things die. How do things
die? How do things pass away?
Whoops, I just gave you a connection!
But, that's up to you to...
What do we call it?
...to explore it.
How do things occur and then pass away?
Chapter 21.
Chapter 22. Why it jumps in here?
"An Investigation of Buddhas."
Wow, that's cool. You
didn't talk about Buddhas
pretty much in this whole book,
and then suddenly, after
investigating time, etc.
you jump off, Mr. A.D.D. Nagarjuna,
you jump off into the
emptiness of Buddhas.
What's that all about?
Where's the connection?
We're going to explore that in Chapter 22.
Chapter 23, really interesting
to explain how this flows
from the last chapter
because Chapter 23
is dedicated to examining the mistake
we make in our life, the
mistakes we make in our life.
Chapter 23 is pretty much
dedicated to mistakes,
especially in perceiving things,
not understanding the emptiness of things.
So again,
it's up to you guys to explore the flow.
I'll give you the six chapters again.
18: persons and things,
the emptiness of Michael
and his universe.
19: we're going to investigate time.
20: when causes and
conditions come all together,
into what I like to call
a consummate convergence.
Perfect convergence of
causes and conditions.
How do we look into the emptiness of that?
How could that not have
potency inherent within it
when all the causes and
conditions are assembled?
How could that not have
some inherent power?
Because things always
pop up right after that.
Chapter 22: we'll look into
Those Gone Thus, Tathagata.
21: is how things occur
and then pass away.
22: is the one with
Those Gone Thus, sorry.
And then 23 is an investigation of error.
All right, like in the chapter
numbers, all right, good.
All right, here we go.
Each time we do a class
together, now starting today,
in this class, I would like to teach you
three important Sanskrit words.
They say that all Buddhas speak Sanskrit
after they've become enlightened,
and they say that the syllables
of the Sanskrit language
have a deep,
almost inexplicable
effect on your chakras,
on your mind, on your body.
Somehow Sanskrit language
has an immediate effect
on your body and mind.
So I thought we could talk a little bit
about the important words in
each chapter that we cover.
And if you were going
to read the Sanskrit,
we're very fortunate that the Sanskrit
for this "Wisdom" book still exists.
We can still read the Sanskrit.
It's a wonderful place
to memorize Sanskrit,
especially the opening two verses.
It's a wonderful place if
you want to learn Sanskrit,
to learn it in the way that
Nagarjuna used Sanskrit,
which is probably one of the
greatest authors in Sanskrit.
So we're going to explore,
going to have an investigation
of three Sanskrit words during each class,
and these are words that are
important for that chapter.
Here's the first one today.
I want to talk about the word 'aātman'.
Say ātman.
- [All] ātman
- Yeah, ātman means BDAG in Tibetan,
which means a self or a self nature.
You probably heard the
word Mahātmā Ghandhi
which means the great being.
'The great self', meaning Ghandhi himself,
Mohandas K. Ghandhi.
So ātman means self or self nature.
I like the parts of this
word. I think it's very sexy.
The 'ā' the initial long
'ā' used to be a short 'a'.
And sometimes a short 'a'
will change to a long 'ā'
at the beginning of a Sanskrit word.
So it used to be atman.
And this initial 'a' in a Sanskrit word,
is called the privitive 'a' in
Greek, it survives in Greek.
And it means 'not'.
So when an 'a' comes at the
beginning of a word in Sanskrit,
it can mean 'not'.
And that survives in English
in words like apolitical,
or atheist, or apathetic,
meaning don't care.
And you see an initial 'a' meaning 'not'.
The root to Sanskrit 'tam', T-M or, T-A-M,
means to be separated.
And so ātman, the word for
self, and the word for atom,
means inseparable, a coherent,
single, unitary, soul.
Soul or self of a thing.
An atom means indivisible
particle, cannot be split.
Once you split an atom
into smaller particles,
it loses its elemental identity,
and it no longer has
unique characteristics
that other atoms don't have.
So atom means that unsplittable,
ātman means a soul,
and when you put ātman in a sentence,
the 'n' drops off, when
you use it as a soul
then it's 'ātma'.
Another example of that is 'yogin',
which means 'a practitioner of yoga',
and then, when you use it in a sentence,
what's it called?
as the noun of a sentence,
it loses the 'n',
it becomes 'yogi', a
practitioner of yoga is a yogi.
But the original form is yogin.
So you might see ātman as
ātma, like in Mahātmā Ghandhi.
And the classical example
of the use of the root tam,
is in this picture that you see here.
This is a classic stone church,
stone temple in Eastern Europe.
And typically they had a wall,
a stone wall would separate the village
from the church or temple.
And then those structures
became called 'temple'.
'The place which is set apart',
so that's a use of the root tam.
A temple is built on that root also.
So atom or ātma means a real self,
a solid core to all things.
Once you say it that way,
does Michael and does Michael's universe
have a solid core,
that's independent of my perceptions,
or independent of my
actions towards others,
independent of my kindness degree,
the amount of my kindness,
that would be ātman?
That would be a solid core to Michael,
which is independent of how
Michael treats other people.
If the world doesn't come from karma,
if the quality of my
life is not determined
by how well I treat others,
then atom, then I'm an ātman.
Then I'm a self-existing
self, and I'm not affected
by how I treat others.
So that's one word I'd like
you to learn in the Sanskrit.
Now, I promised you three.
The next one is skandha,
which means in Tibetan PHUNG PO.
In English,
when we describe a person,
we say 'the body and mind'.
In Buddhism, we say 'the five parts',
the five parts of the person,
and each of those parts
in classical Buddhism
is not called part. It's called a heap,
or a pile, and the Abhidharma says,
,SPUNGS DANG SKYE SGO RIGS KYI DON,
,PHUNG PO SKYE MCHED KHAMS RNAMS YIN,
The reason, why do we call...
Why don't we just say body and mind?
Why do we say the five piles of a person?
It's that each part of a
person, in western terminology,
the mind and the body, they
also have multiple components.
So we don't say body and mind,
we say a pile of multiple
component groups.
Where the word skandha comes from,
if you trace Sanskrit back to older roots,
which are called Indo-European roots,
there's a root, skend-,
and that's the root in English
for scatter and shatter.
So you've got this idea
of a scattering of leaves,
meaning each part of my
body, sorry, my whole body,
and my whole mind, is made
up of multiple, smaller parts
and smaller components.
In that sense, my body and
my mind are both piles.
In classical Buddhism, we
don't say body and mind.
We say the five components
of body and mind.
Mind has four components
and body has one component.
So we have a physical
side of us, one component,
composed of many parts, scatterings.
And then we have the
four mental components,
which is your general awareness;
your tendency to feel at
all times, night and day;
your tendency to discriminate,
this is good, this is bad,
this is tall, this is short,
this is blue, this is green;
and then the other parts of your mind
are classically about 50 other parts
or components of your mind.
They are divided out
in Buddhism to five skandha,
five piles, five heaps
of things which you
consist of. It's important
in the 18th chapter, which is
a discussion of the emptiness
of the person and their parts,
because this is the most typical division
of the parts to a person.
It's the five parts.
In the west, we say body and mind.
When I say five heaps, five skandhas,
five parts of a person, I want
you to think body and mind.
That's like a perfect translation
into western thinking: body and mind.
Does your body have a core,
does your mind have a core?
Do body and mind together,
as Tim, have a core,
an unchanging core, an ātman?
Did I promise you three words?
Did I have a third one here, no, just two.
Sorry about that.
Now I'm going to go back to
the beginning of the chapter.
He says, "when you talk about...
"When you start your
examination of emptiness,"
which is what he's doing
with the 18th chapter.
Now he's specifically starting our journey
into emptiness itself.
He says, "Let's proceed in five steps."
Let's proceed in five steps.
Generally, I'm not
reading you the commentary
because it would take a few years.
But when I see a part of the commentary
which is particularly sexy or interesting,
or will help you understand emptiness,
then I'll pause and
I'll just read straight
from the commentary, so that's
what I'm going to do now.
DANG PO LA LNGA,
When we examine, how do
you get into the idea
that things are not themselves?
How do you first enter?
How do you first take off
into this idea that a
thing is not themselves?
And he says, "Five steps."
If you want to explore how
things are not themselves,
let's look at it from five
different points of view.
Number one.
DE KHO NA NYID LA 'JUG TSUL,
I'm going to describe to you
how you first get into emptiness.
He calls it here suchness,
same thing, tatva.
I'm going to explain to you
how you enter into suchness.
First thing. Second:
LUNG DANG 'GAL SPONG,
Look, I know Buddha talked
about the parts of the person.
I know the Buddha talked about
apparently solid powers of a person.
But look, I'm not contradicting
what he said about people,
in the first turning of the Wheel.
I'm not contradicting that.
What we say when we say
Michael and Michael's parts,
are not coming from Michael
and Michael's parts,
but what we mean by that is clear.
If we can show how we
are not contradicting
what the Buddha said
when he first started to
teach. He talked a lot
about things as if they were solid,
and if they had their own identity,
as if they had their own identity.
And basically, we're just going to show
that in the beginning
of his teaching career,
Lord Buddha talked about things
as sort of concrete things,
because he was warming up
to get to tell you why
they're not concrete.
He was just warming up.
LUNG DANG 'GAL SPONG
We will work out these
seeming contradictions
between the later teachings on emptiness
and the early teachings
on the parts of a person,
in which they seem to be so concrete.
Third topic here, if you really
want to get into emptiness.
DE KHO NA NYID LA BKRI BA'I RIM PA,
What are the proper stages
for introducing these
deep ideas to a student?
You can't just sit down and say,
"Hey, you're emptiness. You're
just made of emptiness."
We should rather have a strategy.
What's an intelligent, effective way
to introduce emptiness to another person?
If you have tried to talk
about emptiness with your
family members, for example,
you have immediately
encountered this problem.
There are skillful ways
to start to talk about
the meaning of emptiness,
for example, in the kitchen.
And there are ways that
you shouldn't start talking
about emptiness, which
will just confuse people.
So the third step here is,
what are skillful ways,
what are skillful strategies
for introducing people to emptiness?
I love the next section, which is,
DE KHO NA NYID KYI MTSAN NYID,
If emptiness itself is empty,
does it have any defining characteristics?
Does it have any special features
which are unique to emptiness?
And it does.
And they are really
sexy. I really like them.
So he's going to talk about
the defining characteristics,
the special features of emptiness itself.
We tend to think that if
emptiness means nothing,
it shouldn't have special characteristics,
or typical features, but
it's quite the opposite.
Emptiness has many
features or characteristics
which are typical of it,
and Nagarjuna's explanation
of those characteristics
is really, it's intriguing,
very intriguing.
Okay, fifth.
DON DE NGES PAR BSGRUB
DGOS PAR BSTAN PA'O,,
And isn't it fitting that the last section
in our introduction to emptiness
should be how are you
going to improve your life
by understanding emptiness?
DON DE NGES PAR BSGRUB
How are you going to put this emptiness
into a practical application in your life
to have a more successful
and meaningful life?
So isn't that a wonderful final category
that we'll be discussing?
You learned this big idea,
this big theory of emptiness,
but how is that going to improve your life
and the lives of other people?
So there we go. Here
we go, now, down to...
I have a picture for you here
of a lady on a swing, I guess.
Yeah, people tend to think, I don't know,
I saw this picture and I
thought, oh this is perfect.
People kind of think that their
relationship to emptiness...
You wouldn't say, "I have
a personal relationship
with emptiness."
It sounds kind of weird. It's like
this lady's boyfriend
is the sun or something.
And the fact is that there are ways
in which you can have a
relationship to emptiness,
almost a personal, intimate
relationship with emptiness.
And that's a big part
of the chapters we're going to cover.
How can you start to have a meaningful,
personal relationship with emptiness?
We'll be going through that.
And then he says, let's
start off on that first,
if you remember the first
category, it was called,
DE KHO NA NYID LA 'JUG TSUL
How should we enter emptiness?
Anybody want to tell me the
special implication of the word
'JUG?
It's the same one as starting off
on a boat across the ocean.
avatara
So how should we get started
on our journey to emptiness?
What are the first steps
we're going to have to take?
And then he says, "Oh, those first steps,
"if they come themselves in two parts."
The first steps you're
going to have to make
to dig into emptiness
has two parts itself.
And normally, I'm not reading
you his whole outline,
which is really a long story
how Choney Lama organizes Nagarjuna,
which is extremely
beautiful, extremely helpful.
But it would take us a year or two.
And I am charting it. I'm
keeping a separate chart
of the, what do you call
that thing, a mind map
Of the outline, and it's beautiful.
I'm keeping it separately,
but it's very complex.
But I have some parts of his outline
that are just too sexy to ignore.
He says, "Entering emptiness,
"like getting into a ship
and starting across the Pacific ocean."
It has two parts.
LTA BA GTAN LA DBAB PA, and
BSGOMS PAS NYES SKYON LDOG TSUL
LTA BA GTAN LA DBAB PA and
The exploration of
emptiness necessarily comes
in two steps.
A personal exploration of emptiness
should involve two
separate steps. Number one:
LTA BA GTAN LA DBAB PA
You have to work hard
to learn the scriptures
that describe emptiness.
LTA BA GTAN LA DBAB PA
means you got to work hard on...
It's what we're doing now
is to struggle your way,
fight your way through the
teachings on emptiness.
You have to kind of submit and surrender.
It's going to be a long
journey through a thick forest.
Many scratchy trees and many muddy spots.
But your first job is
to understand emptiness
in a theoretical way, and
that implies the second step
which is to put it into
practice in your life.
Use it in your life. Use it
to become more successful.
Use it to have a better family life.
Use it to have a better business life.
Use it to be a happier person
throughout the course of your life.
BSGOMS PAS NYES SKYON LDOG TSUL
Second Step.
Use those teachings on
emptiness, meditate on them,
using the personalized instructions
of John and Connie O'Brady.
And by doing so,
LDOG all your SKYONs
Tim? SKYON MIN LDOG
SKYON LDOG
Yeah, stop all your problems in your life.
SKYON means problems in your life.
NYES PA also means
problems in your life.
NYES SKYON
means problem problem.
And LDOG TSUL means
if you meditate on emptiness,
if you get used to emptiness,
you can clean out the crap
in your life, and guess what?
If you, one by one, clean
out the parts of your life
that aren't very nice,
or aren't very happy,
or aren't very successful,
there's this weird experience at the end.
All you're left with is success.
All you're left with is great happiness,
great satisfaction, wonderful life.
If you dig away,
it's like cleaning out your house, right?
Like nowadays I forgot why
I'm trying to clean out my
house, and I go room by room,
mostly tchotchkes,
mostly dumb little things
I have in my house.
I don't use them. I
don't think about them.
I don't even look at them.
And if you're just patient,
and you're methodical,
and you work one by one
through the garbage in your house
and get rid of it mercilessly,
like don't even compromise, don't say,
"Maybe Rosa would like
this," just toss it.
Because she's got limited
space in her house too.
So if you clean out one by one,
the difficult parts of your life,
what you're left with is pure happiness.
That's all you're left with.
So there's the two steps
that already we got
presented to in the study of emptiness.
Number one: go through the theory.
Work through the book.
Work through the ideas.
And then secondly, put them into practice.
Meditate on them, and use them
to clean out the house called "your life".
Throw out one by one the stuff
that's not that important,
or is not very pleasant.
And what you're left with is
an elegant, beautiful house,
like John Brady's house.
I'm going to show you a
picture of a little boy
on two steps.
I was trying to find
a picture of two steps
and I saw this one,
and it kind of got more steps
than two, but two main steps.
And I hope this picture will remind you
the foundation step below his tennis shoes
is what you're doing now. Do the hard work
of understanding the
theory behind emptiness.
And then the second step,
which is where his butt is sitting,
is use that theory in your real life
to clean out the rotten parts of your life
and then all that's left is the beauty
and elegance of your life.
Okay, cool, lets move on.
Oh my gosh there's
another division here...
Okay, I'm still following
the outline, I'm sorry,
but we won't follow it too long.
He says that first
subject we talked about,
which is getting a theoretical
grasp on emptiness,
going through emptiness theoretically.
That itself has two parts.
You got that, Tim, you want to show it?
And by the way, Tim's
doing all this on the fly,
and God bless him, he's doing a great job.
DANG PO LA GNYIS means,
can you further describe
the theoretical study
and background that we should have
to take off across the ocean of emptiness?
And he says, "Yeah, I'll tell
you what it is. These two:"
BDAG NGO BO NYID KYIS GRUB PA DGAG PA
DANG, DES BDAG GI BA NGO
BOS GRUB PA KHEGS TSUL
Say BDAG
Say BDAG GI BA
BDAG means, ātman,
means self, core nature.
BDAG GI BA means, 'of that'.
So when you study emptiness, in theory,
you cover two topics, me and mine.
BDAG means, ātman means me,
and then BDAG GI BA, which means mine.
Why is this important?
When you talk about the Wheel of Life,
when you look at one o'clock
on the Wheel of Life,
and you look at what causes
the Wheel of Life to spin,
it's always misunderstanding
two things: me and mine.
Me and the stuff I own,
or me and my hand, or things like that.
When you explore
emptiness, it's always done
in terms of exploring
the emptiness of Michael
and exploring the emptiness of things
that belong to Michael,
including the world and my hand.
Things like that.
All right, so first, we're going to stop
our misunderstanding of me,
and then we have to stop our
misunderstanding of myself.
No me leads to no mine.
Here's a picture for you guys.
It's supposed to be two feet, I guess.
Oops, yeah, I like this,
the me is your legs.
The mine is your shoes. Get it?
And I was trying to emphasize two things.
Me and mine.
Me ends just before the shoes there.
You have to explore the
emptiness of me and mine
if you want to clean out
then house called your life.
And be left with a clean, elegant house
called nirvana and enlightenment.
Okay, good, all right.
Let's go one more, I'm sorry,
I just want to touch a little
bit more on the outline.
The exploration of me has two parts.
The exploration of me,
when you're talking about
exploring me, that has two parts.
Say, DPYOD LUGS
and GTAN LA 'BEBS PA
DPYOD LUGS
GTAN LA 'BEBS PA
Okay, good.
This is a cool division.
DPYOD LUGS means,
how do you investigate me and mine,
especially me here.
How do you investigate Michael?
Let's go off on an
investigation of Michael.
In fact, Tim is going to
translate a book called
MTHA' DPYOD
which means analysis.
So we have to analyze Michael
and by analyzing Michael, we
will come up with a strategy.
GTAN LA 'BEBS PA
means we'll come up with
a strategy for life.
First we will examine Michael
and then we'll come up
with a strategy for how
to deal with Michael,
how to make Michael happy.
So here's a picture for you guys.
This is Sherlock Holmes.
So he's a famous detective
and this represents the
two steps we have to take
to understand the emptiness
of Michael. Number one:
investigate who is Michael.
Investigate who is Michael, really.
And then secondly, develop a strategy
based on that, for how
to make Michael happy.
First figure out who is Michael,
and then develop a
strategy to make him happy.
That's the two...
So I'm going to go backwards
through this outline.
We're going to investigate Michael
and strategies to make him happy,
because we were investigating me,
and then we're investigating mine. Why?
Because we were going to do
the theory work with emptiness,
and then we were going to do
the practical work on emptiness.
That's all because we
wanted to investigate
the emptiness of the person,
and the parts of the person.
That's the outline that
we're going through.
I'm going to go back to the end here,
and we're actually, oh, I
thought it's a good place now
to show you an image of
the emptiness book that...
We'll do it tomorrow,
we'll do it tomorrow.
I'm going to give you a QR code,
and I'm going to give
you how to get the book
that John and Connie are
going to explain for you guys.
I'll explain it tomorrow.
Okay, here we go.
We have a little bit of time left.
There's a tradition in these teachings.
How much time I got left, five minutes?
Yeah, there's a tradition to jump,
to put your toe in the
cold water. So here we go.
We're going to put our toe into the water
and then we'll swim to Japan.
We're just putting our toe into the water,
and that's the first two lines.
He doesn't even go through
the whole first verse.
He only gives you half of the first verse
'beause he doesn't want to drown you.
And here's the first verse.
,GAL TE PHUNG PO BDAG YIN NA,
,SKYE DANG 'JIG PA CAN DU 'GYUR,
Hang on a second.
Oh, okay, good, it does make sense.
Okay, it says,
,GAL TE PHUNG PO BDAG YIN NA,
If your body and mind were you,
then Tim would have to
be 'ti', I mean 'tu',
I mean 'im', I mean 'um'
I'm not being funny, if you
are only your body and mind,
then since your body and
mind are constantly...
According to Buddhism,
SKAD CIG GIS SKAD CIG GIS
SKYE 'JIG BYED PA'I CHOS
You got to say it twice, and
you got to say it with rhythm.
SKAD CIG GIS SKAD CIG GIS
SKYE 'JIG BYED PA'I CHOS
We had it recently, right?
Yeah, thanks.
Tim is coming into existence
and popping into existence
and popping out of existence.
Millisecond by millisecond.
In Buddhism, we don't see
Tim as a constant flow.
We don't see Tim's body and
Tim's mind as a constant flow.
Rather, they are milliseconds of events
or milliseconds of perception
that are following each
other like da-da-da-da-da.
SKAD CIG GIS SKAD CIG GIS
They are starting and stopping
almost in the same moment,
in a stream of moments.
Tim's body is changing
from instant to instant,
which is you all know that.
You're getting older instant by instant.
Your mind is changing instant by instant.
But does that mean that Tim is
changing instant by instant?
Do we not call him Tim
from the day he was
first christened as Tim
to the day we write his obituary.
Not meaning you'll ever have one.
But you know, we don't
change the name, do we?
The name is constant.
What the name refers to,
the body and mind that the name refers to,
is something that you can't even grab onto
a single moment of it.
It's constantly in flux.
But the name is not in flux, Tim is Tim.
We don't change his name
every time his body changes
because that would be millions of names.
So somehow, we feel
and there's an emptiness here,
We feel that Tim has some continuity.
Tim's body may be changing
from instant to instant, and
Tim's mind may be changing
from instant to instant,
and Tim may own his body
and mind, and Tim may
even be his body and mind.
But somehow, Tim is constant.
We have this feeling. Tim was born.
Tim lived a life. Tim passed
away. It's still Tim, right?
The body is born. The body
goes. The body changes.
The body melts away. But Tim
is the one who had the body.
And Tim didn't change. Tim was constant.
Tim didn't change to Mike,
and Mike didn't change to Rosa
in three minutes of the
change of Tim's body and mind.
It was still all Tim, right?
So he says,
"If the body and mind
have their own existence,
"if the body and mind
exist from their own side,
"then Tim must change
names every millisecond.
Then Tim should follow."
If Tim is the sum of Tim's
body plus Tim's mind,
and if he is self-existent,
if he comes from his own side,
then since the body and
mind are collapsing,
just falling apart from
millisecond to millisecond,
then "Tim" as an idea
and "Tim" as a concept
should change moment by
moment. And he does not.
That's evidence that Tim's
relationship to his body
is not coming from its
own side, all right?
Got it?
So the first place to explore Tim
is to explore his parts.
His parts are his body and his mind.
If his body and his mind are Tim,
and if Tim's body is
changing per millisecond,
and if Tim's mind is
and if Tim is made of his
body and mind together,
then Tim should be
changing by millisecond,
and then, it won't be Tim's body and mind,
it would be Mike's body and
mind in the second millisecond,
and Rosa's body and mind
in the third millisecond.
It should change.
If the relationship is self-existent
between Tim and his parts, if
it's coming from their side
and not from us, especially not from Tim,
then Tim shouldn't last
more than a millisecond.
And in fact, he would be unrecognizable
since that millisecond
wouldn't have a front end
and a back end.
Okay, all right. So, I'll leave you there.
But just one idea to leave you with.
Arya Nagarjuna, his whole life,
was bothered by the
contradictions of life.
That's what made Nagarjuna, Nagarjuna.
He was disturbed by the
inconsistency of life.
I imagine it would
deeply disturb Nagarjuna
if one business strategy led
to success for one business,
and then led to failure
for another business.
For example, if putting
your money into equities
worked for one person and
failed for another person,
Nagarjuna would find
this deeply disturbing.
He would say, "Why?
"It's the same equities.
"Why should one person
make and investment fail,
"and why should another person
make a very similar
investment and succeed. Why?"
It really bothered him.
So, Nagarjuna's approach for us
is to say, "Look, this
stuff, it bothers me.
I don't get it."
And that's how he teaches.
He says, "I don't get it
why Tim should be there
"his whole life, but his body's
changing every millisecond.
"His mind is changing every millisecond.
"Shouldn't Tim be a different
Tim in the second millisecond
"if he doesn't have
the same body and mind?
It bothers me. Something
here ain't right."
Something here ain't right.
If you're starting to feel like that,
then you're starting to
understand Nagarjuna's approach.
Things don't look right.
If things are coming from their own side,
thing's look fishy. Something's wrong.
And his whole life was spent
trying to figure out how to make it right.
All right, let's see
you in the next class.
And we'll get to the answer.